London's crime-fighting ace on his most baffling case!
The Great Mouse Detective is a animation, family,
adventure film directed by Ron Clements.
When the diabolical Professor Ratigan kidnaps London's master toymaker, the brilliant master of disguise Basil of
Baker Street and his trusted sidekick Dawson try to elude the ultimate trap and foil the perfect crime.
Basil of Baker Street / Bartholomew (voice), played by Barrie Ingham.
Professor Ratigan (voice), played by Vincent Price.
Dr. David Q. Dawson / Thug Guard (voice), played by Val Bettin.
Olivia Flaversham (voice), played by Susanne Pollatschek.
Fidget (voice), played by Candy Candido.
Mrs. Judson (voice), played by Diana Chesney.
The Great Mouse Detective (released as Basil the Great Mouse Detective in some countries and The Adventures of the Great Mouse Detective during its 1992
re-release) is a 1986 American animated mystery adventure film produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation and released by Walt Disney Pictures.
Based on the children's book series Basil of Baker Street by Eve Titus and Paul Galdone, the film is
written and directed by John Musker, Dave Michener, Ron Clements, and Burny Mattinson.
Featuring the voices of Vincent Price, Barrie Ingham, Val Bettin, Susanne Pollatschek, Candy Candido, Diana Chesney, Eve Brenner, and Alan Young, the plot follows the
titular mouse detective, Basil of Baker Street, who undertakes to help a young mouse find and save her father from the criminal mastermind Professor Ratigan.
The Great Mouse Detective draws heavily on the tradition of Sherlock Holmes
with a heroic mouse who consciously emulates the detective.
Titus named the main character after actor Basil Rathbone, who is best remembered for playing Holmes in film (and whose voice,
sampled from a 1966 reading of "The Red-Headed League" was the voice of Holmes in this film, 19 years after his death).
Sherlock Holmes also mentions "Basil" as one of his aliases in the
Arthur Conan Doyle story "The Adventure of Black Peter".
The Great Mouse Detective was released to theaters on July 2, 1986, to positive reviews from critics and financial success, in sharp
contrast to the box office underperformance of Disney's previous animated feature film, The Black Cauldron (1985).
The film's timely success has been credited with keeping Walt Disney Animation going after the previous film's failure by renewing upper management's confidence in the
department, thus setting the stage for the Disney Renaissance when feature animated films would become the corporation's most lucrative and prestigious product.
The film explores themes of london, england, detective, queen, mouse, villain.
The tone is lighthearted and mind_bending.